Guide to the Lawrence & Wishart Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lawrence & Wishart records
1927-1951
GEN MSS 703
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.63
(12 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, business and financial records, artwork, and photographs relating to the early years of the British publishing company Lawrence & Wishart, its predecessor company Wishart & Company, and the founding partner Ernest Edward Wishart. Correspondence includes letters to, from, and about various authors, journalists, lawyers, and booksellers, among others. There is extensive correspondence concerning the publication of Jack Butler Yeats's book Sligo (1930), the sales of Nancy Cunard's book Negro Anthology (1934), and the libel case regarding Gerard Kersh's book Jews Without Jehovah (1934). Business and financial records include estimates from printers and binders, sales figures, royalty statements, stocktaking records, loan documents, minutes of director's meetings, and reader's reports. Also present is material documenting the company's involvement in the Publishers' Association of Great Britain and Ireland and its collaborations with the Left Book Club and Workers' Bookshop, as well as original cover artwork for Several Occasions by Mary Butts, among other books.
Lawrence & Wishart
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Company on the Library Associates Fund, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
The Gerald Kersh and George Padmore correspondence is also available on microfilm.
Lawrence & Wishart
Lawrence & Wishart is an independent British publishing company that was founded in 1936 through the merger of Martin Lawrence, the Communist Party's press, and Wishart Ltd., a family-owned liberal and anti-fascist publisher. During the late 1930s, the press was involved in the political and cultural life of the Popular Front, and published literature, drama, and poetry, as well as political economy, working-class history and the classics of Marxism. From 1936 to 1938, Lawrence & Wishart published New Writing, a biannual literary anthology edited by John Lehmann.
Lawrence & Wishart has evolved over the years, but continues to publish works that examine the relationship between politics and culture.
Historical information drawn from the publisher's website: http://www.lwbooks.co.uk/about.html (accessed on 5 August 2010).
Wishart & Company and Ernest Edward Wishart (1902-1987)
Ernest Edward Wishart established the publishing house Wishart & Company in the late 1920s. The company published Scrutinies by various writers edited by Edgell Rickford (the first volume appeared in 1928, and the second volume followed in 1931); Sligo (1930) by Jack Butler Yeats; Negro Anthology (1934) edited by Nancy Cunard; and Jews Without Jehovah (1934) by Gerald Kersh.
Wishart was born in Dulwich, England in 1902, and was educated at Rugby School and Cambridge. In 1927 he married Lorna Garman, the younger sister of his friend Douglas Garman who worked with him at Wishart & Company, and they had two sons, Michael and Luke. Wishart retired from the publishing business in the 1950s and went on to pursue other interests. He died in 1987.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, business and financial records, artwork, and photographs relating to the early years of the British publishing company Lawrence & Wishart, its predecessor company Wishart & Company, and the founding partner Ernest Edward Wishart. Correspondence includes letters to, from, and about various authors, journalists, lawyers, and booksellers, among others. There is extensive correspondence concerning the publication of Jack Butler Yeats's book Sligo (1930), the sales of Nancy Cunard's book Negro Anthology (1934), and the libel case regarding Gerard Kersh's book Jews Without Jehovah (1934). Business and financial records include estimates from printers and binders, sales figures, royalty statements, stock-taking records, loan documents, minutes of director's meetings, and reader's reports. Also present is material documenting the company's involvement in the Publishers' Association of Great Britain and Ireland and its collaborations with the Left Book Club and Workers' Bookshop, as well as original cover artwork for Several Occasions by Mary Butts, among other books.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1927-1948. II. Business and Financial Records, 1928-1951. III. Artwork and Photographs, 1932-1936.
Authors and publishers -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Publishers and publishing -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Anand, Mulk Raj, 1905-2004; Barker, George, 1913-1991; Binder, Pearl, 1904-1990; Blakeston, Oswell; Bose, Subhas Chandra, 1897-1945; Bunting, Basil, 1900-; Butts, Mary, 1890-1937; Cunard, Nancy, 1896-1965 ( Negro anthology); Garman, Douglas, 1903-1969; Kersh, Gerald, 1911-1968 ( Jews without Jehovah); Rickword, Edgell, 1898-1982; Rowe, Newton Allan, 1900-; Wishart, Ernest Edward; Yeats, Elizabeth Corbet, 1868-1940; Yeats, Jack B. (Jack Butler), 1871-1957 ( Sligo); Lawrence & Wishart; Wishart & Company
- Correspondence, 1927-1948; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged largely in alphabetical order by name of correspondent. A group of early correspondence of Wishart & Co. is arranged at the beginning of the series and a group of miscellaneous correspondence is arranged at the end.
  - Early correspondence, Wishart & Co., 1927-1930; 4 (Box 1)
  - "A" General, 1937-1939 (Box 1)
  - Anand, Mulk Raj, 1937-1939 (Box 1)
  - "B" General, 1936-1938 (Box 1)
  - Barker, George, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Blakeston, Oswell, 1937-1939 (Box 1)
  - Bolton, Pitt & Breden, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Bose, Subhas Chandra, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Burt, Brill & Edwards, 1934-1940 (Box 1)
  - Bunting, Basil, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Butts, Mary, 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Byron, Robert, 1937 (Box 1)
  - "C" General, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
  - Cockburn, Claude, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Collett Smith & Co., 1937-1939 (Box 2)
  - Connolly, Cyril, undated (Box 2)
  - Cunard, Nancy, 1937-1939 (Box 2)
  - "D" General, 1937-1939 (Box 2)
  - Davenport, John, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Dunn (H. W. Birks & Co), 1935-1940; 3 (Box 2)
  - "F" General, 1937-1939 (Box 2)
  - Fisher, Frances George, 1930 (Box 2)
  - "G" General, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
  - Garman, Douglas, 1927-1933; 3 (Box 2)
  - Goldring, Douglas, 1930 (Box 2)
  - Greenidge, Terence, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Guthrie, Tyrone, 1937 (Box 2)
  - "H" General, 1937-1939 (Box 2)
  - Heslop, Harold, 1938 (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes drawings by Pearl Binder for book jacket of Heslop's novel Last Cage Down
  - Higgins, Bertram, 1929; 1938 (Box 2)
  - Holtby, Winifred, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Horrabin, Winifred, 1930-1931 (Box 2)
  - James, Norah C., 1937 (Box 3)
  - Kersh, Gerald, 1934-1939; 6 (Box 3)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Also available on microfilm.
  - Lambert, Constant, [circa 1929] (Box 3)
  - Leavis, F. R., 1939 (Box 3)
  - Left Theatre, 1935 (Box 3)
  - Lindsay, Jack, 1929 (Box 3)
  - "M" General, 1937-1939 (Box 3)
  - Mordaunt, Myles, 1934-1939 (Box 3)
  - "P" General, 1937-1940 (Box 3)
  - Padmore, George, 1937-1939 (Box 3)
  - Paramount Printing, 1945-1948 (Box 3)
  - Plomer, William, 1930 (Box 3)
  - Powys, Llewellyn and Alyse Gregory, 1932-1938 (Box 3)
  - "R" General, 1935-1937 (Box 4)
  - Reavey, George, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Richards, Grant, 1930 (Box 4)
  - Rickword, Cecil and Edgell, 1929-1938 (Box 4)
  - Rowe, Newton Allen, 1932-1942 (Box 4)
  - Saffronova (Moscow publishers), 1938; 2 (Box 4)
  - Salt, Henry Stephens, 1938-1939 (Box 4)
  - Scott-Moncrieff, George, 1937-1938 (Box 4)
  - "T" General, 1937-1939 (Box 4)
  - Turner, W. J., 1939 (Box 4)
  - "W" General, 1937-1939 (Box 4)
  - Whyte, Alexander Frederick, 1935 (Box 4)
  - "Wilson", 1938; undated (Box 4)
  - Wintringham, Tom H., undated (Box 4)
  - Yeats, Elizabeth C., 1930 (Box 4)
  - Yeats, Jack Butler, 1931 (Box 4)
  - Miscellanous correspondence, 1927-1940; 3 (Box 4)
- Business and Financial Records, 1928-1951; Series II; 2.71; (7 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or format.
  - Address book of E. E. Wishart, undated (Box 5)
  - Destruction of premises, correspondence, 1940 (Box 5)
  - Estimated income, 1938-1939; 2 (Box 5)
  - Estimates from printers and binders, 1938-1941; 15 (Box 5)
  - Estimates from printers and binders, 1930-1939; 3 (Box 6)
  - Expenses: bills, invoices, receipts, 1928-1938; 2 (Box 6)
  - Figures, 1936-1939; 5 (Box 6)
  - Financial
    - Loans, 1929-1951 (Box 7)
    - Material relating to financial position, 1936-1939 (Box 7)
      Includes proof of Memorandum and Articles of Incorporation of Martin Lawrence and Wishart, Ltd.
    - Personal finance (E. E. Wishart), mostly stock market transactions, 1939-1946 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous financial, 1937-1938 (Box 7)
  - Ledgers
    - Movement of stock, 1932-1935 (Box 7)
    - Record of book sales, 1934-1936 (Box 7)
  - Left Book Club Scheme, 1938-1939 (Box 7)
  - Lenin Works
    - Lenin's Selected Works, notes on stock and sales, 1938 (Box 7)
    - The Teachings of Karl Marx, binder's copy, 1939 (Box 7)
  - Minutes of Meetings of Directors, 1936-1939; 2 (Box 7)
    Also includes sales and financial reports.
  - Memos and related material flagged "For attention", 1938 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1932-1939 (Box 8)
  - Press clippings, 1934-1944; 2 (Box 8)
  - Printed material, 1938-1939 (Box 8)
  - Publicity, 1938, undated (Box 8)
  - Publisher's Association of Great Britain and Ireland, 1935-1939; 6 (Box 8)
  - Publisher's Association of Great Britain and Ireland, 1939; 2 (Box 9)
  - Readers' reports, undated (Box 9)
  - Royalty statements, 1937-1938; 2 (Box 9)
  - Sales ledger accounts, 1934-1936 (Box 9)
  - Stocktaking
    - Printers and binders statements of stock, 1938-1939; 2 (Box 9)
    - Wishart stock, 1937-1938; 2 (Box 10)
    - Soviet Union and the Path to Peace, undated (Box 10)
    - L. W. Stock, 1937-1938; 2 (Box 10)
  - Taxes, 1939-1942 (Box 10)
  - Workers Bookshop
    - "Plebs" (Left Book Club), circa 1938 (Box 10)
    - Liquidation, 1938-1939 (Box 10)
  - A Yell of a Night: movie, 1932-1938 (Box 10)
  - Unsorted material, 3 (Box 10)
  - Unsorted material, 6 (Box 11)
- Artwork and Photographs, 1932-1936, undated; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Cover art for: Several Occasions, by Mary Butts, pen and ink watercolor, signed by Gabriel Atkins, undated (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Cover art for: Ten Thousand Yesterdays, Mrs. Percival Connellan, pen and ink watercolor, 1932 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Cover art by Pearl Binder for: Last Cage Down, by Harold Heslop
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Series I, Correspondence/Heslop, Harold, Box 2
  - Cover art for: Shot Whilst Escaping, by Walter Shönstedt, photographic collage, 1934 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Murder Among Friends, by Simon, dust jacket artwork, 1933 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Two unidentified watercolor drawings, undated (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Photographic portrait, signed "Love, Pippy", 1936 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Photographic portrait, Wieser, Prague, of unidentified man, undated (Box 12 (Oversize))